Finding Aid for Jeremiah G. Turcotte papers, 1933-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jeremiah G. Turcotte papers 1933-2012, 1961-2001
Turcotte, Jeremiah G., 1933-
11 linear feet
2013059 Aa 2
Surgeon specializing in transplant surgery, professor, and Chairman of the Department of Surgery at the University of Michigan. Collection includes publications and presentations, administrative correspondence, biographical records, and documents the history of the Department of Surgery.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received through donations from the Department of Surgery in 2011 (donor no. 10548) and from the Transplant Center (donor no. 10784 ) and Elizabeth Turcotte in 2012.
Periodic additions to the collection are expected.
The papers are open with the exception of some patient/client records.
The Turcotte papers record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Patient/Client Records -- Boxes 7a
Jeremiah George Turcotte was born in Detroit, Michigan on January 20, 1933. He attended the University of Michigan, graduating from the Medical School in 1957 with several academic honors. He remained at the University of Michigan for his internship and residency where he was again awarded for his academic achievements. Upon completion of his residency in 1963, Turcotte joined the faculty of the Medical School as an Instructor in Surgery. By 1971, he had become a full professor of surgery and in 1974, he accepted the position of Chairman of the Department of Surgery, a position he held until 1987. He concurrently acted as Head of General Surgery between 1976 and 1981 and often held multiple administrative positions simultaneously during his career. In 2001, Turcotte became a Professor Emeritus of Surgery.
In 1964, Turcotte participated in the first kidney transplant performed at the University of Michigan and transplant surgery eventually became a major focus of his career. He performed the first liver transplant at the University in 1985 and consistently worked with transplantation at the university, directing the Surgery Transplant Program, the Organ Transplantation Center, the Transplant and Health Policy Center, and the Liver Transplant Program during his career. He also published numerous articles and book chapters on the subject, as well as publishing widely on his other research interests, which included portal hypertension and liver disease. Over his career, his work resulted in more than 195 published journal articles, eight books, and 55 book chapters. He presented just as prolifically, and was invited to lecture throughout the U.S. and internationally.
Along with his service in various organizations and centers at the University, Turcotte was also active in numerous national organizations. He was a founding member of the American Society of Transplant Surgeons and the Transplantation Society of Michigan (later the Gift of Life Foundation). He served as president of these societies, as well as the Central Surgical Association, and the United Network for Organ Sharing (UNOS), the Michigan Chapter of the American College of Surgeons. He served in leadership positions for numerous other organizations and societies, as well.
Amid his many other responsibilities, Turcotte took an interest in the history of the Department of Surgery and gathered numerous materials documenting that history, starting as far back as Moses Gunn, the first professor of surgery at the University of Michigan. He later served on the 150th Anniversary Celebration Committee and assisted in creating a book documenting the Department's history.
Turcotte was the recipient of numerous awards and honors throughout his career. He received the Russel Award from the University of Michigan in 1970 and held the Frederick A. Coller Professorship from 1979 to1989. In 2002, not long after his retirement, the updated surgical library was dedicated in his honor. In 2004, he was given the Distinguished Service Award by the University of Michigan Medical Center Alumni Society, and in 2006, the Jeremiah and Claire Turcotte Professorship in Transplantation Surgery was inaugurated. He also received awards from non-University sources, including the Champion of Hope Award from the National Kidney Foundation in 1996 and the ASTS-Roche Pioneer award in 2005.
The Jeremiah G. Turcotte papers document the career of Turcotte, a transplant surgeon at the University of Michigan, and the history of the Department of Surgery. The collection consists of 11 linear feet and dates from 1933 to 2012, with majority of records dating from 1961 to 2001. The collection has eight series: Personal Files, Publications, Presentations, History, Chairman Records, Patient Records, Audio-Visual Materials, and Slides.
Subjects:
Turcotte, Jeremiah G., 1933-; Medicine--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Surgery.; Transplantation of organs, tissues, etc.; University of Michigan--Department of Surgery.; University of Michigan--Medical School--Faculty.
- Personal Files
  The Personal Files series (0.75 linear feet) includes records related to. Turcotte's personal life and career. Material includes awards and honors received by Turcotte, records relating to various societies and organizations he was a member of, and his professional activity, including his Curriculum Vitae, which includes both a paper copy and a copy on CD. The series also includes a transcript of an interview with the Center for the History of Medicine, which contains extensive biographical information. A copy of the transcript is also included on the CD containing Turcotte's CV.
  - 150th Anniversary Celebration Committee 1997-2000 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Honors
    - Champion of Hope 1996 (Box 1)
    - General 1992-2006 (Box 1)
    - Inauguration of the Jeremiah and Claire Turcotte Professorship in Transplantation Surgery 2006-2007 (Box 1)
  - Biographical 1969-2001 (Box 1)
  - Class of 1957 Reunion Committee
    - Minutes and Agendas 2006-2007 (Box 1)
    - Reunion Booklet 2007 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1990-2004 (Box 1)
  - Donations 1977-2001 (Box 1)
  - "The Father of Transplant Surgery" 2012 (Box 1)
    (includes DVD recording)
  - House Bill 4653, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Memberships and Professional Organizations
    - American College of Surgeons 1978-2000 (Box 1)
    - American Society of Transplant Surgeons 1979-2008 (Box 1)
    - Central Surgical Association 1996-2008 (Box 1)
    - Frederick A. Coller Surgical Society 1949-2002 (Box 1)
    - Frederick A. Coller Surgical Society Presidential Address -- "Chirurgia, Change, and Coller," 1983 (Box 1)
    - Michigan State Medical Society 1989-2002 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Memberships 1979-2009 (Box 1)
    - Transplant Society of Michigan Gift of Life Foundation 2001-2008 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, ca 1972-2006, undated (Box 1)
  - Presque Isle 1992-1994 (Box 1)
  - Press Clippings 1964-2004 (Box 1)
  - Professional Activity
    - Annual Documentation of Faculty Activity 1994-1999 (Box 1)
    - Appointments 1985-2002 (Box 1)
    - Coller Society Retirement Celebration 2000 (Box 1)
    - Continuing Medical Education 1986-2006 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1963-1999 (Box 1)
    - Curriculum Vitae 2006 (Box 1)
      (includes CD)
    - Department of Surgery Library Committee 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Pancreatic Disease Symposium Luncheon Seminar 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - Retirement 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - Transplant Center 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Transcript of Center for the History of Medicine Interview 2006 (Box 1)
    (CD version located with Curriculum Vitae, 2006)
- Publications
  The Publications series (1.25 linear feet) documents Turcotte's publishing history. The series is arranged by publications listed on Turcotte's Curriculum Vitae and publications not on his CV. Articles in the Curriculum Vitae Publications Subseries are arranged based on the categories listed on the CV, then further arranged numerically based on the order publications are listed on Turcotte's CV.
  - Curriculum Vitae Publications
    - CV Chapters in Books
      - #2-5, 8-11 1971-1980 (Box 1)
      - #13-14, 19-20, 22-24 1981-1985 (Box 1)
      - #25-33 1985-1988 (Box 1)
      - #37-39 1989-1990 (Box 1)
      - #42-43, 46, 49, 56 1991-1999 (Box 1)
    - CV Publications (Box 2)
      - #1-9 1961-1964 (Box 2)
      - #11-37 1965-1970 (Box 2)
      - #39-42, 44-55 1970-1974 (Box 2)
      - #56-61, 63 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - #65-69 1976-1977 (Box 2)
      - #72-77 1979 (Box 2)
      - #79, 82-83, 85-87, 89 1980-1982 (Box 2)
      - #91, 93-94, 97-98 1983-1986 (Box 2)
      - #100-119 1985-1988 (Box 2)
      - #121, 123-129 1987-1988 (Box 2)
      - #130-137 1988 (Box 2)
      - #139-143, 145-148 1989-1990 (Box 2)
      - #151, 153, 155-159 1989-1991 (Box 2)
      - #160-176 1990-1993 (Box 2)
      - #178-187 1994-1996 (Box 2)
      - #189-190, 192, 194 1998-2002 (Box 2)
  - Other Publications
    - Abstracts 1985-1992 (Box 2)
    - "The Anencephalic Infant as an Organ Donor for Transplantation: Ethical, Medical and Legal Considerations," undated (Box 2)
    - "The Biliary Tract in Liver Transplantation," 1989 (Box 2)
    - "Cyclosporine dosing and timing: Impact upon allograft outcome, hospitalization time and the cost in the young pediatric kidney transplant recipient," undated (Box 2)
    - "Decompressive Shunts for Variceal Hemorrhage," 1988 (Box 2)
    - "An Empirical Approach to Liver Transplantation for the Alcoholic," undated (Box 2)
    - "Ethics, Alcoholism, and Liver Transplantation," 1993 (Box 2)
    - "GD-MRA in the Evaluation of Vascular Complications Following Liver Transplantation," 1997 (Box 2)
    - "Hepatic Transplantation," Surgery of the Alimentary Tract, 5th Edition, 2000 (Box 2)
    - "Incidence and Management of Biliary Complications after 291 Liver Transplants Following the Introduction of Transcystic Stenting," undated (Box 2)
    - "Infra-hepatic Auxiliary Transplantation with Preservation of the Entire Native Liver in the Treatment of Crigler Najjar Syndrome Type I," 1997 (Box 2)
    - "Liver Transplantation: What Determines Selection?" undated (Box 2)
    - "The MELD System in Liver Transplantation: What Is It, How to Use It, What Will It Mean?" 2002 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Symposium I: Gastrointestinal Hemorrhage (Box 2)
    - "The New Liver Allocation Policy: A Starting Point," undated (Box 2)
    - "Portal Hypertension," Surgery: Scientific Principles and Practices, 2nd Edition, 1994 (Box 2)
    - "The Potential of Presensitization as a Prognostic Factor in Cadaveric Renal Transplantation," undated (Box 2)
    - "Recent Advances in the Treatment of Shock," undated (Box 2)
    - Reviews/Commentary 1989-2002 (Box 2)
    - "Total Portal-Systemic Shunts," 1988
- Presentations
  The Presentations series (0.75 linear feet) documents lectures, presentations, and talks given by Turcotte. The first part of series, the Talks subseries, contains lists of slides used for 247 presentations given by Turcotte and is tied to the Slides series. The list of slides for presentations includes the category and slide number of each slide used in the presentation. The Presentations series also includes presentations listed on Turcotte's CV. These presentations are arranged numerically based on their listing on the CV. Finally, there are materials for presentations not listed elsewhere.
  - Talks
    - Index (Box 2)
    - 1-15 1962-1974 (Box 2)
    - 16-50 1974-1979 (Box 2)
    - 51-75 1979-1983 (Box 3)
    - 76-100 1983-1986 (Box 3)
    - 101-120 1986-1988 (Box 3)
    - 121-170 1986-1992 (Box 3)
    - 171-205 1992-1996 (Box 3)
    - 206-240 1996-2000 (Box 3)
    - 241-247 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - CV Visiting Professorships
    - #70, 102, 119, 134, 148, 158, 172, 173, 176 1989-2001 (Box 3)
    - #98 Global Review 1989 (Box 3)
    - #178, "Transplantation an Affirmation of Life," 2005 (Box 3)
  - "Ethics," 2004 (Box 3)
    (includes CDs)
  - General Surgery undated (Box 3)
  - Resident Talk -- Kidney Transplantation/Overview of US Transplant System 2004 (Box 3)
  - "Organ Transplantation and Immunology," 2003 (Box 3)
  - Portal Hypertension/Cirrhosis/Liver TXP Student Lecture 2005 (Box 3)
  - "The Story of Transplantation: From Myth to Mice to Man" Student Talk 2004-2005 (Box 3)
  - "Surgery and Surgeons at the University of Michigan," 1981 (Box 3)
  - Transplantation undated (Box 3)
  - "Transplantation: A Frontier for Bioethics and Bioscience," undated (Box 3)
    (includes mini-cassettes)
  - "UNOS, DOT and the Private Sector," 2002 (Box 3)
  - Variceal Bleeding in Cirrhosis of the Liver Panel Discussion 1976 (Box 3)
- History
  The History series (3.5 linear feet) documents the history of the Department of Surgery at the University of Michigan, and dates back to the 1850s. The series includes a subseries documenting the lives of various notable professors of surgery at the University of Michigan, one documenting the history of the Department of Surgery, and a photographs series.
  - Professors of Surgery
    - Cabot, Hugh 1983-1997 (Box 3)
    - Child, Charles Gardner 1977-2000 (Box 3)
    - Coller, Frederick Amasa 1937-2004, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Coller, Frederick Amasa -- Pictures undated (Box 3)
    - Coon, William Warner 1995-2000 (Box 3)
    - Crosby, Alpheus Benning undated (Box 4)
    - Crudup, Jimmy 1985-2006 (Box 4)
    - Darling, Cyrenus Garrett undated (Box 4)
    - Davenport, Horace Willard, 1991 (Box 4)
    - deNancrede, Charles Beylard Guerard 1996 (Box 4)
    - DeWeese, Marion Spencer, 2002Fry, William James 1974-1990 (Box 4)
    - Green, William Warren undated (Box 4)
    - Greenfield, Lazar 2001-2007 (Box 4)
    - Gunn, Moses 1979-1997 (Box 4)
    - Lyster, Henry Francis Lehunte undated (Box 4)
    - Maclean, Donald 1872 (copy)-1979 (Box 4)
    - Maddock, Walter Grierson circa 1962 (Box 4)
    - McGraw, Theodore Andrews 1929 (Box 4)
    - Penberthy, Grover Cleveland undated (Box 4)
    - Pitcher, Zina 1982 (Box 4)
    - Ransom, Henry King 1933-1983 (Box 4)
    - Sloan, Herbert 1983-2004 (Box 4)
    - Thompson, Norman W. 1979-2003 (includes CD) (Box 4)
    - Vaughan, Victor Clarence 1982 (Box 4)
    - Youngblood, James Peter undated (Box 4)
  - Department of Surgery
    - "150th Anniversary: A Commemorative Portfolio," 1999, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 150th Anniversary Book 1981-2000, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Burn Center 1974-1986 (Box 4)
    - Creation of Section of General Surgery 1966-1967 (Box 4)
    - Emergency Services 2004 (Box 4)
    - Events 1999-2006 (Box 4)
    - General History 1952-2003 (Box 4)
    - General Surgery 1962-2003 (Box 4)
    - General Surgery Chief Residents 2000-2003 (Box 4)
    - Guest Book 1988-2001 (Box 4)
    - Medical Center and Hospital History 1986-1993 (Box 4)
    - Pediatric Surgery 1974-2006 (Box 4)
    - Plastic Surgery 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - Portraits 1978-1991 (Box 4)
    - Publications 1976-1999 (Box 4)
    - Rules and Regulations and Bylaws 1965-1971 (Box 4)
    - Thoracic Surgery 1996-2000 (Box 4)
    - Transplantation History 1985-2007 (includes CD) (Box 4)
    - "The University of Michigan Eye Center: A Centennial Project 1981 (Box 4)
    - Vascular Surgery 2005-2007 (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - Donated Pictures -- Turcotte, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Donated Pictures -- Cotzin (Box 5)
    - Faculty -- Donated Photographs, 11 folders (Box 5)
    - Faculty Photos (Box 5)
    - Class Photos (Box 6)
    - Class Photo Directories, 1956-1960 (Box 6)
    - Commencement Pictures, ca 1967 (Box 6)
    - General Surgery Staff and Class Pictures 1938-1982 (Box 6)
    - Photo Albums
      - Henry K. Ransom 1957-1983 (Box 6)
      - Letters to Dr. Ransom 1967-1983 (Box 6)
    - Framed Pictures
      - Surgeon's Club Photograph 1936 (Box 6)
      - Surgeon's Club Photograph 1940 (Box 6)
      - Surgery Staff Photographs, 1933/34-1936/37, 4 items (Box 6)
- Chairman Records
  The Chairman Records series (0.5 linear feet) includes records from Turcotte's service as Chairman of the Department of Surgery. The series includes correspondence between various administrators and reports.
  - Coller, Ethel 1983-1988 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    - Dickinson, David 1974-1975 (Box 7)
    - Frey, Charles W. (Wayne County General Hospital) 1974 (Box 7)
    - Fry, William J. 1974 (Box 7)
    - Gronvall, John A. 1973-1979 (Box 7)
  - Dean Review 1980-1982 (Box 7)
  - Department Review 1972-1980 (Box 7)
  - Department Review Correspondence 1980 (Box 7)
  - Director of Surgery Administration 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - Emergency Services 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - General 1972-1985 (Box 7)
  - General Surgery-GYN Agreement 1980-1982 (Box 7)
  - Intradepartmental Review 1979 (Box 7)
  - Medical Service Plan Implementation 1974 (Box 7)
  - New Hospital 1974-1976 (Box 7)
  - Plastic Surgery 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Shapiro Letter on Reorganization 1982 (Box 7)
  - Thoracic Surgery 1974-1981 (Box 7)
  - Vascular Surgery 1974
- Patient Records
  The Patient Records series (0.5 linear feet) includes operation records from Turcotte's residency, and early transplant records, including patient records from a Home Records Book. Records were removed from the Home Records Book binder and foldered by patient.
  - Home Records Book II
    - Brooks 1967-1969 (Box 7a)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2069 ]
    - Brown, M. 1968 (Box 7a)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2068 ]
    - Hankerson 1968 (Box 7a)
    - Johnson 1967 (Box 7a)
    - Masters 1967-1968 (Box 7a)
    - Nagel 1967-1968 (Box 7a)
    - Nicholson 1967-1968 (Box 7a)
    - Plock 1967-1969 (Box 7a)
    - Warner undated (Box 7a)
    - Wetzel 1967-1968 (Box 7a)
  - Surgery Records
    - First Assistant Operations -- Clinical 1957-1958 (Box 7a)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2058 ]
    - Junior Year
      - First Assistant Operations, 1962-1963 (Box 7a)
        [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2063 ]
      - Major Operations 1962 (Box 7a)
      - Minor Operations 1962-1963 (Box 7a)
    - Senior Year -- Major Operations 1962-1963 (Box 7a)
  - Transplant Records -- Early Examples 1965-1967 (Box 7a)
    [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2067 ]
- Audio-Visual Materials
  The Audio-Visual series (1 linear foot) includes a variety of media, including 16mm film, VHS cassette tapes, and mini-cassette tapes.
  - Intra Uterine Kidney Transplant -- Film Reel (Box 8)
  - U-Matic Video Tapes
    - Hepatic Resection with the Ultrasonic Knife (Box 8)
    - Extraperitoneal Cystic Duct Drainage of the Bile Duct in Liver Transplantation (Box 8)
    - Dr. Jeremiah G. Turcotte (Box 8)
  - Film Reels
    - Unknown (Box 8)
    - Portacaval Shunt (Box 8)
  - VHS Cassettes
    - James Crudup Story 2006 (Box 8)
    - Turcotte 16mm Films (Box 8)
    - Coller, et al (Box 8)
  - Unlabeled minicassette tapes (10) (Box 8)
- Slides
  The Slides series (3 linear feet) includes file cabinets of slides used in various presentations given by Turcotte (see the Presentations series). The slides are housed in the original cabinets in the order maintained by Turcotte and are accompanied by a binder listing slides by category and number and giving a description of the contents of each slide. The slides include a variety of content such as diagrams, surgical procedures, facilities, and historical images.
  - Slide Index Binder undated (Box 8)
  - Drawer 1
    - PA (Pancreatitis) (Box 9)
    - TD (Transplant Donor) (Box 9)
    - PT (also TP -- Transplantation Pancreas) (Box 9)
    - HTr (also LTr -- Liver Trauma) (Box 9)
    - TH (Transplantation Heart) (Box 9)
    - A (Anatomy) (Box 9)
    - CP (also CPa or CPA -- Cancer-Pancreas) (Box 9)
  - Drawer 2
    - P (Portal Hypertension) (Box 9)
    - LHA (Liver-Hepatic Assist) (Box 9)
    - TX (also X -- Xenotransplantation) (Box 9)
    - LG (Liver-General) (Box 9)
  - Drawer 3
    - T (also TK -- Transplantation-Kidney) (Box 9)
    - TL #249-671 (also LT -- Transplantation Liver) (Box 9)
  - Drawer 1 (Box 10)
    - Empty (Box 10)
  - Drawer 2
    - H (History) (Box 10)
    - TG #337-356 (Transplantation General) (Box 10)
  - Drawer 3
    - G #1117-1165 (General) (Box 10)
  - Drawer 1 (Box 11)
    - TG #1-336 (Transplantation General) (Box 11)
    - LT #8-603 (also TL -- Transplantation Liver) (Box 11)
  - Drawer 2
    - CL (also CLi -- Cancer-Liver) (Box 11)
    - CB (also CBR or CBr -- Cancer Breast) (Box 11)
    - C (Cancer, possibly also CBD -- Cancer Bile Duct) (Box 11)
    - TLu (Transplantation Lung) (Box 11)
    - M (Miscellaneous Humor) (Box 11)
    - LB (also LBT -- Liver Benign Tumors) (Box 11)
    - TI (Transplantation Immunology) (Box 11)
    - OP (also TPr -- Organ Preservation) (Box 11)
    - Sch (Box 11)
  - Drawer 3
    - G #1-1167 (General) (Box 11)